Jonas Oppenlaender

September 25, 2020

Contact Crowd Computing group

Information Center for Ubiquitous Computing

https://github.com/joetm

jonas.oppenlaender@oulu.fi

University of Oulu Pentti Kaiteran katu 1 90570 Oulu, Finland

http://www.jonaso.com

Birth date: 11. Feb 1981 Nationality: German

Summary I am a last-year PhD student with a keen interest in applying AI and crowdsourcing

to configure spaces for the future of work that are fair, accountable, and transparent. I research and develop web-based mixed-initiative interfaces and socio-technical

systems that empower, support, and augment humans.

EDUCATION

May 2018 - Present Doctoral student, Computer Science

University of Oulu, Crowd Computing group

Oulu, Finland

Dissertation: Crowd-powered Creativity Support

Advisor: Associate Prof. Simo Hosio

Aug 2014 - Nov 2015 Master of Science, Computer Science

University of Southampton, Web Science Institute

Southampton, United Kingdom

Thesis: CrowdUI - A Remote Tool to Crowdsource and Evaluate User Interfaces

Advisor: Associate Prof. Thanassis Tiropanis

Graduated with distinction

Jan 2013 – July 2013 Certificate in Business Analysis

University of Toronto, School of Continuing Studies

Toronto, Canada

Aug 2005 – July 2006 Erasmus exchange student

Linköping University, Institute of Technology

Linköping, Sweden

OCT 2002 – MAR 2011 Diplom-Wirtschaftsingenieur (Master of Science in Industrial Engineering)

Technical University of Darmstadt

Darmstadt, Germany

Thesis: Applying the Kano model to analyze social product requirements

1991 – 2000 General qualification for university entrance (Abitur)

Gymnasium am Deutenberg Villingen-Schwenningen, Germany

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

May 2018–Apr 2021 Doctoral Researcher

University of Oulu Oulu, Finland

- Working independently on my own research projects under multiple deadlines

- Produce and present research papers at internationally leading conferences and events (
- Planned and executed experiments
- In-person interviewing of study participants and questionnaire administration
- Fullstack web development (JavaScript/React, Python, PHP) and cross-mobile development (Monaca/PhoneGap/Cordova)
- Data analysis in R
- Developed academic research partnerships and cooperation with leading universities and professors in the area
- Organized two workshops at top international conferences (CHI '19 and C&C '19)

Aug 2016-Apr 2018

Research Assistant (Wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter)

Freie Universität Berlin, Human-Centered Computing Group Berlin, Germany

Project IKON:

- A solution for facilitating internal knowledge transfer at the Museum of Natural History, Berlin, with a touch-screen based visualization of research activities based on a formal ontology
- Developed an ontology (fub-hcc.github.io/IKON-ontology) and a software architecture for integrating and processing heterogeneous data from different sources
- Managed the research group's intranet (Confluence and Jira)

Aug 2016-Mar 2017

Research Assistant (Wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter)

Interdisciplinary Cluster of Excellence "Image Knowledge Gestaltung" Humboldt University of Berlin Berlin, Germany

Project ID+LAB:

- Linked data based interactive visualization of interdisciplinary research activities at the Cluster of Excellence
- User modelling, use case development, and empirical studies (interviews)

Professional Experience

$May\ 2016-July\ 2016$

Full-Stack Open Data Developer

Liip AG

Bern, Switzerland

Developed open data solutions using modern web development practices in an agile Scrum team.

Stack: Python (Django, CKAN), JavaScript (Vue.js)

Projects:

- SBB Open Data Platform (opentransportdata.swiss)
- Eurapco Trend Observatory (eurapco-trends.com)

OCT 2015-APR 2016

Linked Data Developer

Seme4 Ltd.

Southampton, United Kingdom

Research and development of linked open data solutions.

Stack: Python (CKAN), PHP, PostgreSQL, JavaScript

Advisors: Dr. Ian Millard, Dr. Hugh Glaser

Lead developer for the SkillsPlanner linked data project (<u>skillsplanner.net</u>),
 an InnovateUK-funded research project for solving the skills gap in London's construction industry

- Development of CKAN data management and linked data conversion tools
- Redesign and refactoring of the <u>sameAs-Lite</u> service

Aug 2013-July 2014

IT Business Analyst

Alstom IS&T Paris, France

- Analysed, defined and designed new IT services and processes:
 - Served as liaison to the functional service owner to translate business requirements into efficient and highly usable solutions
 - Managed the service transition, conducted the final acceptance testing and presented the results to the service catalogue governance board
- Beta tested the corporate end-user IT service web portal
- Developed and managed the IT service catalog through four iterations
- Drafted and translated IT service-related communications to the 90,000 employees and IT support groups

June 2011-Mar 2012

Strategy Analyst Trainee

Alstom Power Baden, Switzerland

- Improved the internal idea management system and process
- Migrated the Power Business division's intranet to Microsoft SharePoint
- Automated the generation of PowePoint presentations for KPI reporting with macros in Excel
- Supported the strategic planning

2008 - 2013

Freelance Full-Stack Web Developer

Darmstadt, Germany

Full-Stack web development and community administration

Stack: PHP, JavaScript

- Developed my own online social network website (with over 228,000 members)
 and a geo information website with crowdsourced content
- Promoted online partner programs as an affiliate webmaster

July 2010-Aug 2010

Volunteer

Local Economic Development Department

Radoviš, Macedonia

2000-2002

Military Service Franco-German Brigade

Donaueschingen, Germany

RECOGNITIONS AND AWARDS

Sept 2020 Invited Member of Doctoral Consortium at Mensch und Computer '20

June 2020 Invited Member of Doctoral Consortium at EICS '20

June 2019 Invited Member of Graduate Student Symposium at Creativity & Cognition '19

Nov 2015 Distinction, University of Southampton

SCHOLARSHIPS AND GRANTS

Total funding (personal grants) received: 26 710 EUR

Sept 2020 Jenny and Antti Wihuri Foundation Grant 5000 EUR

June 2020	Riitta and Jorma J. Takanen Foundation Scholarship	$1500 \; \mathrm{EUR}$
May 2020	Finnish Foundation for Technology Scholarship	$5000 \; \mathrm{EUR}$
Mar 2020	Tauno Tönning Foundation Grant	$5000~\mathrm{EUR}$
DEC 2019	Nokia Foundation Scholarship	$5000 \; \mathrm{EUR}$
Aug 2005	Erasmus Sokrates Scholarship, DAAD	$1100 \; \mathrm{EUR}$
Sept 2020	Course grant, University of Oulu UniOGS	$500 \; \mathrm{EUR}$
June 2019	Travel grant, ACM SIGCHI	US \$1800
May 2019	Travel grant, University of Oulu UniOGS	400 EUR
May 2019	Travel grant, University of Oulu UniOGS	1000 EUR
Ост 2018	Travel grant, Ubicomp/ISWC	US \$600

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Co-Teacher, University of Oulu

2019 – 2020 Social Computing (521044A, 30+ students, 5 ECTS, Bachelor)

Spring 2019, Spring 2020, Autumn 2020 (schedule change)

Responsible for organizing, managing, and holding all exercise labs, including

mini lectures at the beginning of each lab

Teaching Assistant

2020, 2019 Human Computer Interaction (521145A, 145+ students, 5 ECTS, Bachelor)

Autumn 2018, Autumn 2019, Autumn 2020

2019 Applied Computing Project I (521152S, 3 students, 10 ECTS, Master)

2016–2017 Software Project (4 students, Bachelor and Master)

Web-based game for collaboratively annotating digitized images of the cultural

heritage archive at the Department for Art and Visual History, Humboldt

University Berlin

Curriculum planning

2019 Social Computing (521044A, Bachelor), University of Oulu

2018 Semantic Web Technologies (19305401, Master), Freie Universität Berlin

STUDENT SUPERVISIONS

Sept 2020-today Bachelor thesis, Katri Säily

Dec 2018–May 2019 Technical supervisor, Master thesis, Antonio Kongjonaj

June 2018-Aug 2018 Summer project, Antonio Kongjonaj

Jan 2018–Apr 2018 Bachelor thesis, Bastian van de Wetering

DEC 2017-APR 2018 Master thesis, Ömer Bayram

DEC 2017-APR 2018 Bachelor thesis, Andre Slava Paderow

Aug 2016-Apr 2017 Master thesis, Immanuel Pelzer

Nov 2016-June 2017 Software Project, 3 students

Dec 2016-Apr 2018 Supervision of two student research assistants

ACADEMIC SERVICE

OCT 2020 Student Volunteer, UIST '20, Virtual

June - Aug 2020 Organizing Committee, Int. Conference on Design Creativity (ICDC 2020), Virtual

May 2019 Organizer, Workshop on Designing Crowd-powered Creativity Support Systems

(CHI '19), Glasgow, UK

June 2019 Organizer, Workshop on Crowd-Powered Interfaces for Creative Design Thinking

(C&C '19), San Diego, CA

Jan 2019 Associate Chair, CHI '19 Late Breaking Work

June 2019 Student Volunteer, Creativity & Cognition (C&C '19), San Diego, CA

OCT 2018 Student Volunteer, Ubicomp/ISWC '18, Singapore

June 2018 Organizing Committee, UBI Summer School 2018 (UBISS '18), Oulu

Apr. 2018 Program Committee, Studierendenkonferenz Informatik (SKILL '18), Berlin

Peer Reviewer

2020 CHI, UIST, IUI, EICS, CSCW, MobileHCI, Human Computation Journal

2019 CHI, UIST, EICS, CSCW, C&C, INTERACT

2018 IMWUT, CSCW, CHI PLAY, HICSS, ICMI, ESWC

CERTIFICATIONS AND LICENSES

2014 Scrum Master (Scrum Alliance)

2014 Certified Associate in Project Management (PMI)

2014 ITIL v3 Foundation (Axelos)

2013 Certificate in Business Analysis (University of Toronto)

2013 Quality Manager (German Accreditation Body DAkkS)

Zend Certified Engineer PHP 5 (License No. 013105)

2009 Business English Certificate Higher (University of Cambridge)

LANGUAGES

German Mother tongue

English Very good (TOEFL 114/120, IELTS 8)

French Beginner

Spanish Beginner

Memberships

ACM Association for Computing Machinery

SIGCHI ACM Special Interest Group on Computer-Human Interaction

GI Gesellschaft für Informatik e.V.

IEEE Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers

References

Primary Simo Hosio, Associate Prof. simo.hosio@oulu.fi

Supervisor Crowd Computing group

Center for Ubiquitous Computing

University of Oulu

Secondary Denzil Ferreira, Associate Prof. <u>denzil.ferreira@oulu.fi</u>

Supervisor Community Instrumentation and Awareness group

Center for Ubiquitous Computing

University of Oulu